Guide to the Edward Flanders Ricketts Papers, 1936-1979 (inclusive), 1936-1947 (bulk)
Department of Special Collections
- Manuscripts and notes, Series 5
  - "'Competition,' being 'The history of Mr. Loving-Kindness and his begats.' Part one of ...", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - "Philosophy of breaking through, latest draft" (includes two EFR photographs), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - "The curious vortices of M-124" with comments by EFR, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - "Education and the three levels of intelligence", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - "WPA - Private employment contrast", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - "Outline of an inner plan (probably essay IV, born of a great need", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - "Charts for study of genius", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - "Participation" (possible title for a book of essays), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - SEA OF CORTEZ, 2nd edition, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Review of Elwood Graham show by EFR; pg from Chicago Daily News, Dec. 10, 1941(no clear reason - review of SEA OF CORTEZ cut out and filed with other reviews in folder 29) (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Reviews of The Moon is Down, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - The New Republic, 9 Dec. 1940.Article on Steinbeck, p. 785 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Sea of Cortez (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - San Francisco Chronicle, Dec. 14, 1941,, Scott Newhall, Joel W. Hedgpeth
    - Saturday Review of Literature, Dec. 27, 1941,, Donal Culross Peattie
    - New Republic, Feb. 16, 1942,, Stanley Edgar Hyman
    - New York Herald Tribune Books, Dec. 7, 1941,, Howard N. Doughty, Jr.
    - Monterey Peninsula Herald, Dec. 6, 1941,, Beth Ingels
    - New Yorker, Dec. 1941,, Clifton Fadiman
    - Time, Dec. 22, 1941
    - New York Herald Tribune, n.d.,, Hewis Gannett
    - Chicago Daily Tribune, Dec. 10, 1941,, Fanny Butcher
    - Carmel Cymbal, Dec. 1941,, F.C.C.
    - New York Sun, Dec. 11, 1941,, Robert Wilder
    - Chicago Daily News, Dec. 10, 1941,, Sterling North
    - "The First Reader", Harry Hansen
  - "Class Anthozoa; Sub-class Alcyonaria" (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - "Annotated phyletic catalog and bibliography, class Anthozoa, subclas Alcyonaria"
    - "Record of Alcyonaria sent to Dr. Deichmann as a result of the PBL Spring 1940 Gulf of California trip"
    - EFR notes
  - "SF Bay Area Book" (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - "Suggested outline for a handbook of marine invertebrates of San Francisco Bay Area."
    - "Zoological preface"
    - Organization of Bay Area book, outline, and notes
  - "Memos for III (completely revised) edition, Between Pacific Tides, after 1941 reprinting" (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - "Start card file of errors and additions..."
    - "Corrections and comments on BPT, Dr. S. Stillman Berry"
    - "Suggestions for changes in the text of Between Pacific Tides "
    - "Suggestions and corrections for Ricketts and Calvin, G. Piternick "
      (stapled to "Suggestions for changes....")
    - "Guide to the intertidal hermit crabs of the Pacific coast of US and Canada" (including sketch)
    - "Example of treatment"
    - "(Definitive Ed) Between Pacific Tides "
    - "Chitons that have specific ecological..."
    - "Additions to Betw[ee]n Pac[ific] Tides "
    - "Changes for II edition (post 1941) of Between Pacific Tides "
    - "Also see my personal copy"
    - "Annotated phyletic catalog and bibliography, list of abbreviations"
    - "Errors"
    - "New edition of R+C, 1939"
  - Author's abstract of Sea of Cortez (including revised version) (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - "Miscellaneous thoughts in process" (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - "Dedication"
    - "Factors in the distribution of animals"
    - "Ecology and sociology"
    - "Is there such a thing as race?"
    - "Vs atom bomb experiment"
    - Pencil drawings
    - "Vector, etc."
    - "Notes from Encyclopedia Britannica re: vector analysis"
    - "Can tie in the proceeding with the following classifications of the stages of consciousness"
    - "The obvious and important fluctuations..."
    - "'Idealism' vs. what I call 'Reality'"
    - "The question of orbits..."
    - "Squares [in a system of -10-]"
    - "Physical imprint"
    - Quote of clipping from Monterey Herald sent to John [Steinbeck] re: divorce case
    - "The true world is unknowable..."
    - "Random dispersal vs. 'order'"
    - Notes on relations of women and men
    - "The idea that 'everything is everything'"
    - "Thoughts regarding the difficulty of postulating any method..."
    - Notes on reading
    - "Explicit vs. implicit"
    - "Problem"
    - "The central experience"
    - "Adjustment"
    - "Nightmare"
    - "Now I am feeling very blue..."
    - "Two things"
    - "That chess is (or very may well be) symbolic of life..."
    - Sheet blank except for word "Chess"
    - "Personality analysis"
    - "Other notions that can be worked up"
    - "I write vs. I please"
    - "A crystalizations..."
    - "Universality"
    - "On the nature of phenomena"
    - "Exposition of the nature of spiritual..."
    - "I wonder if there is ready to be crystallized..."
    - Concert program
    - "An easily understood way of saying it"
    - "Possibilities to account for environmental influences..."
    - "Worth remembering concepts arrived at or considered during 1932 BC Alaska trip"
    - "With this life"
    - "Extra-humanism"
    - " Literary Digest Fall 1936 poll"
    - "Statistics"
    - "Merges into one symbolic synthesis..."
  - Between Pacific Tides (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - "Marine Plankton of the Pacific Coast"
    - "Preface to the revised edition (BPT, February 1947addenda)"
    - "Forward by John Steinbeck (Nov. 1941 printing)"
    - "Feb. 1947 addenda"
    - "Plankton essay"
    - "Plankton essay bibliography"
    - "February 1947 printing. Title page changes"
    - "For the new edition..."
    - "Carlisle, John G., R., 1945 'The technique of inducing spawning...'"
    - "The units comprising human society..."
    - "Stephenson, T.A., 1947. 'The constitution...'" [pg. of references]
    - "BPT Febr. 1947 addenda. Errata"
    - "BPT Plank essay"
    - "Summary (and recommendations)"
    - "Plankt essay"
    - "Memo before plankton essay is completed"
    - "SU Press plans"
    - "SU Press. Material to turn over to them for new ed BPT"
    - "John G. Carlisle..."
    - "Science..."
    - "Spawning in time..."
  - "Zoological introduction to BPT" (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "Waveshock MS" (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Photos maps (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Sardine article MS" (incl. published copy in 7 Mar. 1947 Monterey Peninsula Herald (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - "British Columbia Sardine" (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - "Statistical tables"
    - "History of the Pilchard Fishery of British Columbia"
  - "The California Sardine (1)" (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Old folder with EFR notes
    - "Introduction"
    - "Organization of the scientific article"
    - "Figures required"
    - "Statement of plankton in general - Qualitative"
    - "Statement of plankton in general - Quantitative"
    - "Sardine-important plankton production on the Pacific Coast"
    - "Unallocated"
    - "Food of the Sardine (2)"
    - "Discussion"
    - "Recommendations"
  - "The California Sardine (2)" (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - "Absolute Extreme" graph
    - Library charge cards
    - "Note..."
    - Daily News (Los Angeles, CA, 19 Jan. 1948) article "They're only poor fish..."
    - "Fri Harbor"
    - "1919-1927 Hopkins Marine Station"
    - "Absolute Extremes" graph
    - "Data on maximum and minimum"
    - "Org. of plankton"
    - "Org. of Diatoms"
    - "Food chain"
    - "Data for estimation"
    - "Average monthly surface temperatures, Pacific Grove, CA"
    - 7 pages EFR sardine notes
    - "A one line rubber stamp...
    - "If you could determine..."
    - "Absolute Extreme" graph
    - "The extent of northward migration..."
    - "Today the news..."
    - "A tenable hypothesis..."
    - "Factors in a) the abundance of sardines; b) the accessibility of sardines at Monterey"
    - "Between Season changes"
    - The California Sardine
    - "Annual tonnage of sardines landed in California" graph
    - Order for 8x10 print
    - "Notes on the fisheries situation in British Columbia, summer 1946"
    - "California Sardine (Pilchard) and Pacific Herring"
  - "The Oregon Sardine, the Washington Sardine, the Mexican Sardine, the High Seas Sardine." (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Old folder with EFR notes
    - "Seasonal total tonnage"
    - "In the early days..."
    - "Total landings" graph
    - "Estimated tonnage received"
  - "Statistical reports: The California Sardine." (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - "The tide as an Environmental Factor." (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - "CalPac-Related Biological investigations" (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - "Definitive report on plankton..."
    - "Thoughts and suggestions for possible future work"
    - "Suggestions for statistical and graphic analyses..."
    - Letter from W.E. Allen (1946)
    - Diatom tables
    - "Friday Harbor"
    - Tables
    - "Plankton Production figures"
    - Graphs from Scripps Institute
    - "Sardine article"
  - "CalPac-Related Biological investigations: General" (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - "Bipolarity and the Soupfin Shark"
    - "A comparison between the West Coast NA"
    - "Upwelling along the coast of Chile-Peru"
    - "Soupfin Shark"
    - "Data for ordering supplies and equipment, etc."
    - "Data for ordering slides"
    - "Thots [sic] on possible coop research, PBL and CalPac"
    - "The Pismo Clam"
    - "The percentage of Oil in Diatoms per dry weight"
  - "Chemical data resulting from CalPack experience starting August 1, 1943" (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - "Sardine Stockwater Concentrate"
    - "Red Carubic [?]"
    - "Method for protein in fish meal"
    - "Ethylene Oxide"
    - "Recap of Sardine Meal Analyzed, Season 1943-1944"
    - "Production of Sardine Meal"
    - "Production of Sardine Oil"
    - "Analysis of fresh sardines"
    - "Protein anaylsis of 20 sardine meals"
    - "Monterey new results"
    - "Lab results"
    - "58 to 60% at start"
    - "Formula for Buffer F"
  - "Misc. Scientific Statistical Summaries, Zoography, etc." (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Map of Baja
    - Graphs
    - "Zoogeography"
    - "Non. temp. - Panam-Overlap"
    - "Thoughts on Zoogeography"
    - "Schmidt 1921 data on distrib."
    - "Decapods"
    - "Information I want on Pac. coast Decapods"
    - "Marine Zoogeography"
    - "Shallow Water Summary"
  - "Natural Selection" (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - "1937 Collecting reports" (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - "Carpenter, Philip P. 1856. 'Report...'"
    - Collecting reports
  - "Data from Previous Trips" (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - "Westwards towards Asia"
    - "Idea for Northern trip"
    - "Bering Sea"
  - "QC and W Cst Vanc Id Mss, Synoptic Keys" (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - "Stubbs Island, Calyoquot, List of spp. Recap"
    - "Chief..."
    - "Descr..."
    - "Stubbs Island, Calyoquot, List of species"
    - "Data on Collecting Stations"
  - "Data on Reproductions, methods, etc." (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - "When first ed of Btwn Pac Tides..."
    - "Data for reproductions..."
    - "Add to illustration folder"
    - "Birds of America"
    - Self-Portrait of Audobon
    - Hen Turkey and Young
  - "Commercial trips: Southern" (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - "Data for next trip to Gulf"
    - "Shell vials"
    - "Large Projects"
  - "Commercial trips: Northern" (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - "Plan"
    - "Possible Modus Operandi"
    - "Possible Summer 1942 Trips"
    - "Possible Locations"
  - "Travelling Kit" (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - "For Cat Embalming..."
  - "Newport Bay-Ensenada trips" (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - "Take along..."
    - "Plan"
    - "Trip South"
  - "Philippine Trip: Spring 1941" (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - "1946 Alaska Trip" (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - "Workmen out in back"
    - "Aleutian, Gulf Alaska..."
    - "Put with specifications for trip equipment"
    - Outline Map, North and Central America
    - "Sending package..."
  - "Copy of notes on trips to West Vancouver Island and the Queen Charlotte Islands, prepared by Edward F. Ricketts for the use of John Steinbeck, 1948" (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - "Excess or duplicate papers" (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - "The Four Letter Word" [poem] (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - "Use and Nostalgia" (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - "Nostalgia-Projection"
    - "What's wrong with the world"
  - "Plans for a book on the Mandated Islands, 1945-1946" (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - "Modus Operandi
    - "Letter to Professor Clyde"
  - "Transcript of summer 1945 and 1946 notes based on trips to the outer shores, W. Coast Vanc., Queen Charlotte Is., etc. New Series Note books 3 & 4." (Box 13 (OS), Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous material, Series 6
  - Sacramento Sectional Aeronautical Chart (Box 13 (OS), Folder 8)
  - Pacific Biological Laboratory embosser in blue felt bag (Box 13 (OS), Folder 9)